If you aren't doing it hands-on, your
opinion about it is very likely to be
completely wrong. This is Mark Brooker.
He's a distinguished engineer [music] at
AWS, and I interviewed him for technical
learnings from his career. 3,000 cloud
system postmortems. I want to ask you,
what makes a good postmortem? I could
spend a lot of time talking about that.
You had a tweet that said that there are
cases where caches are bad. I prefer to
see the teams around me avoiding caching
where possible. We also discussed how
software engineering is changing. What
is important given that code is kind of
flowing like water now? The job changes,
and and and you do different work.
For someone [snorts] who's structuring
their career, would you say it's better
to be overrated or underrated?
Here's the full episode.
At some point, when I was a very junior
engineer, I looked at the more senior
engineers and said, "What what is the
difference between you and I? I'm
working more hours than you. I'm I'm you
know, landing more code than you. Why is
it that you're so much more impactful
than I am?" And then I realized that
kind of the direction of your work, like
what is the thing that you're actually
shipping, matters more than the volume
of your work and your contributions.
What would be your advice on how do you
find problems that matter?
Yeah, I think you have to go super
broad. So, I think there's a set of
those things that come in from from
customers, from the world, right? Like,
here is an unsolved problem.
You know, I spend a lot of time meeting
with AWS customers and listening to them
talk about, you know, what are the
things they still find difficult in in
our space. What are they, you know, what
are they investing in? Where are they
spending their time? Where would they
prefer to be not spending their time and
and focus on their core business
instead. And so, that's one rich seam
of ideas and and and focus on what's you
know what's interesting. I think
completely at the other level is
sort of on looking at the technical
trends and you can look at just the the
kind of speeds and feeds like wow,
networks have gotten faster, storage has
gotten faster. You know, we've seen this
huge explosion in in multi-core and now
in GPUs and you know, so there's a
bottom-up innovation trend there too,
which which you can also look at and say
well, this enables all of these new new
things.
And
um and then broadly kind of
across the world like what what are the
big trends that are going on? What are
the things that are changing in our
industry? What are the things that are
changing in in the world and really it
is those kind of moments of change that
have the
you know, bring with them the
opportunity to to to build things and
and and to recognize problems.
And so to pick one, you know,
concretely, uh you know, when I was in
uh working on the Lambda team in in in
2020 and
I was talking to a lot of customers
about you know, they were super excited
about building on serverless, they were
super excited about building on
containers, there'd been this massive
shift and
what people were seeing then was wow, I
love these serverless products, I love
building this way, but the world of data
and especially relational data doesn't
fit super well into this this paradigm,
right? These relational databases are
still very serverful, you know,
fantastically powerful products, but but
not kind of operationally the same. And
you know, that thinking was you know,
this felt super important to me of like
wow, these customers have have brought
to me a gift of of understanding
something that's really important and
and so I joined the Aurora team, we
built Aurora Serverless and then we
built uh we built the sequel. You know,
we've been investing deeply across all
of our database products to make them a
better fit for these
um
you know,
uh serverless and and and container
workloads.
And
that is an example of of a trend that
was brought by, you know, brought by a
customer.
Um but then also these trends that have
been driven by kind of architectural or
um by other things going on, right?
Faster networks, faster compute, faster
connectivity. It's one of the big
technical trends in the database world
right now is
uh this sort of block storage becoming
the
default back end, the default uh
durability layer for uh for databases of
all kinds, from analytics workloads to
online workloads. And there's been this
incredible explosion around that. And so
if you look at what we did with Aurora D
sequel, for example,
you know, that was
very much learning from that trend and
and taking a lead on that trend and
saying, "Well, we're going to make S3,
this this block store that we built uh
you know, 20 years ago
uh sorry, object store that we built 20
years ago
uh the
underlying
uh durability layer of this new
database. But obviously it doesn't have
the latency properties or or or the rich
interface that that that an online
database needs. And so we're going to
build an architecture on top of that
that deals with all of these other
things
in a much better way, but doesn't have
to worry about durability.
And you know, so that was this perfect
collision of a set of things I was
hearing from customers and a set of
things that were technical trends coming
together and thinking, "Wow, we've we've
got this opportunity to build something
now that is going to be a market leading
product um that would be hard to imagine
without either of those, you know, input
signals."
I I saw something that you wrote. You
mentioned that you were on call for 15
years somewhere in there. And I've heard
many stories of more senior engineers
negotiating out of on-call because per
unit time it could be perceived as not
that impactful.
And so why did you stay on-call for so
long?
I would say that the
majority of
my in-practice knowledge about how to
build distributed systems has come from
being on-call
and
analyzing and deeply understanding
these postmortems and and and COEs.
Um
you know, one of the one of the
challenges of of, you know, running a
company like AWS and and running
large-scale systems is that folks come
out of college with great often great
knowledge of computer science
fundamentals, great programming skills,
you know, great mathematical skills, all
of that stuff is fantastic.
But that without the grounded knowledge
of what it actually means to run and
understand, you know, understand
systems.
And, you know, on-call is one of the
best ways to learn those things, best
ways to see,
um you know, how do systems really run?
How do they really behave? You know, how
do customers really use them? What
happens when customers use systems in
unexpected ways? How can we make systems
more resilient to to customers using
them in in in different ways?
And I think that should be almost a goal
of on-call, right? If you have folks in
your teams who are on-call and they're
just closing the same ticket over and
over. Well, you know, that's where you
need to just build some automation. And
again, building automation is easier
than ever, it's more powerful than ever,
fantastic.
Um but where you really want to spend
the time of the deep experts on your
team is, you know, here's something
unexpected or or unusual that's happened
in in the system. Let's deeply
understand that and let's bring that
knowledge back to both improving that
system and communicating broadly to
the the company and and and the outside
community what we've learned from that.
And so one of the most you know one of
the most uh
powerful things we do at AWS is we have
this mechanism of a very broad weekly
meeting where we all get together, you
know, engineers from across AWS,
leaders, senior leaders from across AWS
and talk about COEs, these postmortems
that we write.
And what we can learn from them.
And how we can apply those lessons
across the whole company. And I think
that
particular mechanism, that particular
kind of in Wednesday morning meeting
that we have
um is one of the things that has been a
core
uh almost causal factor behind you know
AWS's success.
Uh because it has allowed us to and
forced us to spend leadership bandwidth,
to spend expertise, to spend the time of
our best engineers deeply understanding
how our systems operate and why they
operate the way they do.
Um
and you know that level of being just
extremely grounded in reality
uh
helps you design better products, help
helps you architect better systems.
You know, helps you think more clearly
about uh the the next round of things,
helps you fix, you know, helps you fix
issues. And so it's this fundamental
kind of learning exercise. It's a real
blessing.
Um
so I would you know I would recommend on
call to to anybody who wants to learn
about the practice of of distributed
systems. And I would certainly recommend
spending time reading COEs, reading
postmortems, and and deeply reflecting
on not only what can we fix tactically,
but what can we fix organizationally and
strategically and what kind of tools
might might need to exist to to prevent
this kind of thing happening again.
And you know, you asked earlier about,
you know, where do ideas come from? This
is another, you know, fantastic kind of
flow of ideas of saying,
"Wow, you know, we seem to be solving
the same problem over and over in
different ways and getting it slightly
wrong every time."
Um you know, can we extract a a tool to
do that? Can we build a service around
that? Can we Can we build a feature
around that to make it easier for us to
get right and and and easier for our
customers to to get right?
Yeah, it's interesting because I think
if you ask most engineers, they they
really avoid on-call, but it sounds like
you you kind of go towards it and you've
learned a lot from it because it's a
major source of customer problems.
Yeah, and again, you know, I think for
me it comes down to optimizing for
finding the most important things to
work on and you know, if you aren't
close to operating your actual system
and you don't know how it's actually
working,
how are you supposed to identify what to
fix, right? You can come up with some
theories about those, but they're
probably not going to be right.
Um
and again, like I I I don't think
there's a huge amount of value in
the rote ticket closing work of on-call.
I think automation, you know, should be
doing those kinds of work, but I think
there's fantastic value in, you know,
deep understanding, deep investigations
and and deep reflection on what you
learn from
postmortems and COEs.
I tried to estimate uh a couple of
months ago for a talk how many industry
postmortems and Amazon COEs I'd I'd read
over my career.
The best estimate I could come up to and
this was about a year ago, was was
between three and 4,000.
Um and so uh you know, even a little bit
of lesson from each one and it tends to
you know, tends to stick.
Yeah, that was my next question
actually. I I looked at the slides from
that internal presentation and it said,
"I've read approximately 3,000 cloud
system postmortems from across the
industry." And my immediate thought was
I want to ask you what makes a good
postmortem.
So, I think you know, what makes a
really great postmortem is first really
getting into the details and making sure
that you deeply understand what happened
rather than just assuming what happened
based on on the biases you bring in.
Um and so there's a kind of lesson one
there is if you can't understand what
happened, well that teaches you
something about your logging and metrics
and observability and you know, and and
simulations and all of these other
things.
And then once you deeply understand what
happened, um then the ability then a
great postmortem steps through
the whys behind that at multiple levels,
right? Like why? Well, yeah, there was a
code bug. Okay, sure. Code bugs, yes, we
can fix that, but we can't stop there,
right? Like why was that missed in
testing and validation?
You know, for these reasons. Uh you
know, what can we improve? What can we
build around those? Okay, next step you
know, why you know,
why was our testing and validation where
it was? Or you know, why did we assume a
certain thing about the behavior of the
system that we wouldn't have assumed
before?
And so as you sort of get through these
deeper and deeper layers,
a a great postmortem not only identifies
kind of fixes to the proximal cause, but
also identifies broader fixes to
technology, to organizations, to you
know, products and and and and so on.
Um and so that's a kind of multiple
levels thing, right? And you can't get
stuck on
you know, what is the the the most
proximal cause of of an incident, but
you also can't get stuck on this, well,
you know, things fail sometimes and what
are we going to do about it? And
um you you have to come up with a set of
you know, really concrete action items
to fix things at different levels. Fix
this particular line in the software
that that caused something, you know,
fix the testing processes that that
didn't catch that, you know, fix the
um you know, maybe social or or team
processes that led to those technical
processes. Um
and you know, and then if you're seeing
patterns across multiple postmortems,
sort of level those up and say, well,
clearly there's a hard underlying
problem here. You know, can we build a
service around that? Can we build a
library around that? Can we build a
you know, community of practice around
that? You know, are there technical
changes we can make uh to to avoid whole
classes of things?
Um
So that's quite a long-winded answer,
but I I I do think it is it all flows
from
understanding and understanding at
multiple levels. Like understanding
immediately like what happened, but also
understanding you know, broadly what
happened, you know, technologically and
organizationally and and and in context.
And then the ability to connect that
particular event or or postmortem with
other ones, you know, and and and and
extract those patterns.
You know, one of the things that we we
did in D SQL was we spent a lot of time
as we were designing that looking
around, you know, relational database
related postmortems and thinking about
both our own and our customers and
thinking about, you know, how can we
design a database that helps people
avoid falling into these traps?
Um
and, you know, a really common kind of
outage pattern folks with relational
databases is
you have a client
on a distributed system, starts a
transaction, and then goes out to lunch
for whatever reason. And, uh, you know,
that could be a GC pause or could be a
lossy network or it could be a loss of
connectivity and now it's holding locks.
Um and so, if you look at, you know,
relational databases, they don't tend to
be resilient to clients misbehaving in
that way. And that's a really common
cause of
uh, operational issues for systems built
on relational databases. And so, as we
were designing D SQL, we were thinking,
how do we avoid
uh, broadly that class of problems? And
so, folks can say, "Hey, I'm going to
build on D SQL and just not have this
whole class of problems."
Uh, and, you know, I think that's a
really kind of powerful
outer loop over the postmortem process
is to say, "How do we turn all of these
lessons into new services and into
service improvements?"
How do you prevent misbehaving clients
from being a problem for the database?
Yeah, so in in D SQL's case, um
we have uh, we have no pessimistic
locking. And so, it the within the scope
of a transaction, uh, everything that
happens in that transaction, all of the
reads happen using this mechanism called
multi-version concurrency control, where
every row in the database, we sort of
store a history of versions. And so, you
can read an old version of a row without
blocking writers and saying, "Hey, you
can't you can't update this cuz I just
read it."
Um and then, you know, locally within
the query processor that's handling a
connection, uh, we spool the rights
locally and then you get to commit time
and we do this optimistic check of uh,
you know, can I commit this transaction
at at at the transaction commit time.
And so, combining those two mechanisms
of having multi-version concurrency
control and and the scale-out storage
that comes with it
and the commit time optimistic checks,
we can strongly say that, you know,
there is no way that a reader of a piece
of data can block other writers and
there's a no way that that a writer of
data can block readers.
Um, writers can block writers, but only
um,
only by changing data, not just by
looking at it. And so, you can, you
know, you can say, well, you know, I can
cause, um, Sorry, writers can't block
writers, but they can prevent other
writers
uh, transactions from eventually
committing by making a bunch of changes.
And that is
inherent to the definition of the
particular database isolation level. Out
of curiosity, in practice, what percent
overhead would you expect for keeping
copies of old rows for the sake of those
stale reads? Yeah, it's actually
surprisingly small. And it's
surprisingly small because if you look
at the access patterns for most online
databases, even ones that do a lot of
write traffic, that write traffic tends
to be quite concentrated. Uh, and, you
know, it's quite unusual for an online
database workload or even an analytics
workload
to
make a second version of every row in
the database. Typically, what it's doing
is making a,
you know, first, second, third,
hundredth version of this row and a
fiftieth version of that row, but the
vast majority of data isn't changing.
And so, it's super workload dependent,
uh, as as is everything in in in the
database world, uh, but the overhead
tends to be relatively small.
Uh,
I would say it's unusual for
a online database workload for that
overhead on storage to be more than
about 10%.
From my experience, I've seen an
interesting dichotomy between teams
where some teams they really understand
postmortem culture. They tend to be
infrastructure teams. They tend to take
it really seriously and everyone in on
those teams, the tech leads are asking
you, "Hey, why why did that happen?" And
you know, really follow up and make sure
it's it's not a problem. Then I've also
noticed on other teams that is less of a
strong muscle. For those teams that
don't take it too seriously, what would
be your your pitch for why they should
take it seriously?
Yeah, it all comes down to where you
want to spend your time, right? Do you
want to spend your time improving your
product and and making it better or do
you want to spend your time
uh fighting the same fire over and over?
And uh you know, really the
culture of building
um
you know, building great postmortem
cultures to make sure that at the the
the
pros- at the product level and at the
organizational level,
um
you are
fixing known issues
and you are avoiding having the same
problems multiple times.
Um and typically when I see teams that
have you know, a poor postmortem
culture, I think they're
probably one of two failure modes there.
You know, one of them is a
lack of focus on just the outcomes,
right? Like, you know, a lack of of of
really
um
I wouldn't say caring enough. I think
that's a little bit too too personal,
but being really focused on on, you
know, is this
is this product performing super well?
Are we you know, are we really making
our customers happy? And that is
fundamentally a cultural and and and
leadership cultural problem
of of setting the right standards. Oh,
and by the way, like I don't think, you
know, standards should be
uh you know, should be uniform, right?
Like there are places where you know,
the details really really matter where
things like durability are just critical
and and and you do need to have super
high standards in those places.
Um
and you know, places where
you want to optimize for other things
and and and maybe have, you know, have
have a a higher production defect rate.
And I think that's that's okay.
Um as long as that's an intentional
decision that's being made. So, that's
kind of case one, right? Like
insufficient focus on the outcome.
I think case two, and and this is a
harder one to change,
is normalization of kind of operational
heroics. Like, we don't need to fix
these root causes because our on-calls
are super heroic and they're going to
stay up all night and they're going to,
you know, they're going to hack around
things and they don't mind being paged
100 times a week. And
they can feel from the inside like it's
a good culture, right? Like, oh wow,
these people are super strong owners.
They're super engaged. They really care.
They're really working hard on call.
And those are all good signals. But then
when you look at it from the outside,
it's like, well, we're not actually
fixing the causes of things. We're just
doing this fantastically expensive
investment of taking all of these people
and their strong ownership and their
expertise and spending them just on on
on this break-fix cycle.
And that's where you need to kind of
look at it from the outside and say,
well, let's take this energy of this
team, fantastic energy, and focus it on
uh on on improving the service, getting
getting out of the cycle, finding, you
know, finding new things to fix, finding
new things to build.
And that can be hard because it can be
hard for, you know, those folks who've
been in that mode to look at it and say,
"This feels so good. It feels really
like we're we're caring about our
customers and caring about our product
and caring about our business."
Uh, to realize that oh, no, we're
actually caring about it at the wrong
level and we're not serving our business
in the best possible way by being so
narrowly and tactically focused on this
break-fix cycle. And that's where you
sort of need to pop them out and say,
"Well,
let's spend more time thinking about the
postmortem. Let's spend more time
thinking about the causes of things.
Let's let's spend more time addressing
these things in a more uh, strategic
way." And wow, okay, now you've got so
much more time to do that because you've
broken the cycle and you can improve
your product in different ways. I mean,
since you have worked on AWS for almost
two decades, uh,
I'm sure you have a lot of experience
building distributed systems and I think
one of the most common advice that you
hear, I guess this is maybe in the
context of system design, is I I almost
hear almost 100% of the time people will
say, "Just throw a cache on it." Or you
know, you'll have a system design and
say, "How do you make it better? Let's
put a cache here. Let's put a cache
there." And I saw you had a tweet that
said that there are cases where caches
are are bad despite people saying it's
best practice. I was curious if you
could explain that. Yeah, so caching's
good, right? Like it's hey, I'm I'm
going to uh, take the these core ideas
from computer science of of temporal and
spatial locality and I am going to
exploit those to make my system faster,
scale better, et cetera. And so, you
know, obviously very attractive. But,
the downside of caches, especially in
distributed systems, is they have this
mode, right? Like they have this um you
know the there's a mode where the cache
is full, and the cache is full of the
right data in time and space to perform
very well.
And there's a mode where the cache is
empty or contains the wrong data.
And
in the first mode, the system is fast
and happy and healthy.
In the second mode, the system is slow,
often down, because now the back end
doesn't scale to deal with
all of this under-cache traffic.
Customers are very disappointed.
Um
and often it is down in a stable way.
And this is this kind of idea of
meta-stable failures, where the system
has has um
switched from state one to state two,
and in state two it's still stable,
right? Like it's still it's down, but
it's not going to come back up under its
own energy, because for example, all of
this traffic is causing a huge amount of
contention in my database, or it's
saturating the network, and so I can't
even refill the cache. It's not even
getting the right kind of data in.
And so, you know, when I talk about the
downsides of caches, it's really about,
you know, how do we avoid that modality
between
you know, fast and you know, uh the that
that failure of caches, and the you
know, how do we avoid the state where
we're down?
Um
And so, if I go back to
to DSQL, like our answer there is DSQL,
what we call the storage tier, is
essentially a cache, but it is a
complete cache. It contains every row in
the database.
Um and so, it doesn't have this mode
where how do I recover from it being
empty or containing the wrong data? It
contains all of the data.
Um
similarly, if you look at a a more,
let's say, classical relational database
design like Aurora,
the Aurora leader is constantly telling
the potential failover targets, "Here's
something you should cache. Here's
something you should cache."
So, when a failover happens, the cache
is warm on, you know, on on the failover
target. Um and so, those are the kinds
of things that you can do to avoid those
modalities.
But, in general,
um
you know, and I I I wouldn't extract
this as a rule or or or
or or say that, you know, this applies
100% of the time,
but in general, I prefer to see the
teams around me avoiding caching where
possible.
I prefer patterns where you have a,
let's say, complete materialized view of
the data if you need very fast access to
it, especially if it's slow moving. Just
pull it down onto your local machine and
work with it in memory.
You know, if it's only being updated
once a week, who cares? Like, just make
lots of copies of it.
Um
Uh so, that's that's one pattern. Or,
you know, use a scalable back end, you
know,
or Dynamo DB or whatever your favorite
scalable database is,
and keep your database vendor honest
about getting to the the scale and
performance you need, rather than
putting a cache in front of things.
So, caching isn't a bad pattern, but it
is a pattern with some
significant downsides that are, you
know, really
uh best avoided.
In practice, how how often do you see
that metastable failure, though? Yeah,
you know, this is uh it's not it's not
super common, right? Like, you might go
years without seeing, you know,
something like that. But, if you look
across
the biggest, most impactful,
uh you know, system postmortems across
the industry, I would say that these
kinds of metastable failures have been
an underlying cause in probably a
majority of them. And
it's super important that, you know, as
an industry and as a community of
practice, we understand those things
deeply because
the also those cases where these do
happen,
you know, tend to be larger-scale
issues, longer recovery-time issues, and
and and more complex-to-fix issues,
right? Where you have to often, you
know, turn it off and turn it back on
again, which is this very very painful
thing for a a a team or an organization
to do.
Um
and you know, and so again, like you you
might go years operating a system with
seeing nothing like this. And and but if
you look at the most impactful issues,
it's actually fairly common as an
underlying cause for those issues. And
so, you know, it's kind of both of these
things of being quite uncommon and being
being rather common.
I was reading your blog and you have a
series of posts on how AI may impact the
future of software engineering. And I
kind of want to pick your brain on that.
So, what's your perspective on how you
think AI will uh impact software
engineering and how it'll change things?
Yeah, I mean, it's, you know, hard maybe
harder than ever to tell the future. And
so, you know, this is a a set of uh
maybe guesses uh and and and predictions
about about the future. Um
So, I'll I'll say the first thing I I,
you know, I deeply believe about
software is
we have only just started to see the
impact that software is going to have on
the world. There is such an opportunity
for
more software to exist, bigger software,
better software, more personal software.
You know, all of these things. And so,
software has, throughout its well, its
60-ish-year history, been
supply constrained.
And, you know, I think that's going to
remain true. I think the opportunity for
for software in the world is is just,
you know, almost almost unbounded.
Um and that's really exciting, right?
It's really exciting to be at a moment
when
the economics of building software are
changing and and are changing rather
quickly.
Um and that gives us an opportunity to
think about what could we do in the
world with a lot more software?
Um you know, a lot more
software personalization, a lot more
just the right software in the right
place at the right time.
And
you know, that gives me a huge amount
of, uh, you know, excitement about the
future of of this industry,
uh, because, you know, we we have a
massive opportunity ahead of us, both
driven by these changing economics of
software development.
Um
now, also with those changes, there are
going to be needs for, you know, us as
software practitioners, people who build
software, people who who love software
to to adapt. And, uh, you know,
that that means that that software
careers are going to look different. Um
uh, they're going to look different
early on, they're going to look
different later on. I think the software
business is going to look different. And
the
um
success of people and organizations over
the next, uh,
you know, next who knows, 5 years,
decade, is going to be largely
predicated on their ability to adapt to
that change and and to lead that change.
You told the story about this guy who
bet on analog circuits when, obviously,
we know digital became kind of the more
more dominant way.
Yet, he made he made good money. For the
people who maybe don't want to adapt,
you could still get by and succeed. It's
not going to be like a crazy thing. Is
that is that kind of the takeaway and
why you brought up that story? Yeah, I I
I I I
I think that's that's the right
takeaway. And so if I sort of break
down, you know,
the the the world into to three tiers, I
you know, I think there's going to
remain a huge amount of joy in the craft
of software. Um,
you know, like the craft of of joinery
with, you know, with handsaws, right?
Like it's it's a nice way to spend time.
It's not a particularly economically
interesting activity anymore, but not
everything we do has to be an
economically interesting opportunity. It
can just be something I do because I
enjoy it, because I enjoy the product of
it, because I enjoy talking to people
about it, right? And so there is, you
know, I I I don't think that is going to
go away. I think we're going to see,
you know, a lot of interest in in that.
Like there's been interest in in
retrocomputing and, you know, people who
run an Apple II as their desktop. And
like, well, again, it's wildly
impractical. It's not economically
interesting, but it's fun and something
I, you know, could do as a hobby. And
so, you know, that's that's going to be
a remaining part of of of the world of
software for probably forever.
Um, and then there's this this, you
know,
kind of story that that I told in the
blog post.
And I think this relates to,
you know,
driving change in the real world it's
always harder than it looks from the
outside, right? Like as you get into the
details things become more difficult.
They become more dependent on people.
They become more dependent on politics
and policy and um,
you know, our our various
irrationalities as humans. And And so
driven by that,
you know, there is going to be a
huge amount of and a shrinking over time
amount, but it but a huge amount of the
software industry that is run
in what I might call the old way, right?
Past techniques, past languages, past
technologies.
And there's real economic opportunity in
engaging with that part of the, you
know, part of the world. Um you know, as
we saw with with analog electronics,
analog electronics will very much exist.
In fact, there are
parts of the world like, you know, like
radio and power systems where there's
been incredible technology technological
advancement in in in those fields.
Uh but they have become more niche, and
so, you know, digital became the
mainstream. We wouldn't be talking like
we are today
if it wasn't for this uh you know, 12
orders of magnitude or whatever
explosion in in digital transistor
counts.
Um
but there's interesting opportunity
there, and I think that interesting
opportunity is going to change shape and
and and become more and more specialized
and and and more and more niche and and
great careers to be built there.
Um and then there is the mainstream,
which I think is going to adopt these
new technologies from agentic
development to AI-powered development
to, you know, specification-driven
development um and, you know, a whole
lot of other, you know, new things whose
names we don't even know yet
um
to build software at a speed and a cost
that is unimaginable to do with with old
techniques.
And I think that is where correctly the
majority of the industry is going to be
going. I think that's where the majority
of careers are going to be built. I
think that's where the majority of um
economic opportunity is. It's the space
I'd be in if I was building a company
today. It's the space I'm in in my role.
Um and you know, the one I would sort of
personally be most excited about.
But yeah, it isn't only one. I think
there's going to be the spectrum of
software practice, and especially where
software engages with the physical
world, uh there are going to be some
really interesting
questions about how do we bring these
new technologies, how do we bring these
new practices into
the various many niches that software is
going to and has, you know, over over
six decades kind of wormed its way into.
It's interesting you mentioned joinery.
I wonder if
down the road
we'll see apps on the app store that
people pay extra for because it's
marketed as this was written by a human
or it's it was written by hand. It's a
bespoke
you know, custom app.
Crazy how the world's going to change.
But so it sounds like you know, change
is obviously the the common case. It's
the one that we should be thinking
about. Maybe we can break up the
conversation into parts. One is for
junior engineers.
What is important given that code is
kind of flowing like water now?
At risk of being a bit meta about our
past conversation, it really is about
finding those problems that matter and
and and doing that early in in a career.
And
you know, that requires an understanding
of customers. It requires an
understanding of the business. It
requires an understanding of of
economics and and and of systems.
And
that can I think that's going to move
from being
you know, almost kind of senior engineer
work of like oh, well, you know, now
you're going to go and talk to customers
and actually understand the context of
the stuff you're building
to being more and more part of
even the earliest steps of an
engineering career. Right? Like here's
the context. Here's the problem. Here's
the customer. Let's go off and work
together and solve
you know, and and and and solve this
problem with all of this context.
And
I think that's going to be
super exciting for one set of folks,
uh, and a little bit frustrating for
people who have come into um,
you know, looking for a pure software
development career, right? Looking for a
career where they sit down, open their
IDE,
start typing and and don't stop for
eight hours. I think that's going to be
a mode that we're going to see fewer
people in and a mode that's going to be
harder and harder to build a career
around. Now, the other mode of, "Oh, I'm
excited to go off and learn from my
customers about what they're building
and what they need." I think that's
going to be ever more highly, you know,
highly valuable. And so, super exciting
opportunity to build,
you know, build careers there.
And then maybe and and this might come
across as being a little bit, um, you
know, paradoxical. I think there's also
a ton of opportunity for, you know,
folks who are extremely technically
deep, um, you know, who are, uh,
you know, deep on optimization problems
or deep on infrastructure problems or
deep on, you know, various scientific
things or deep on databases or deep on,
you know, one of the many, many topics
that are all behind our industry.
Because I think the ability to
ans- ask the right questions is also
much more valuable than it was has ever
been.
And so, I think there is a ton of
opportunity for people coming into the
industry with deep technical or
scientific knowledge to now leverage
that in ways that, you know, maybe were,
um, were hard before, right? There was
too much sort of boiler plate to really,
you know, to really use that leverage
that you have. And so, I think we're
going to see a lot more of of of those
kinds of careers, of really kind of
building expertise in a technical topic,
in a scientific topic, and then be able
to turn that into software and software
products in a way that
was really difficult before, and in some
cases wasn't possible before, and is now
um you know, vastly easier.
If I was to look at a career ladder's
expectation, some of what you described
of maybe engaging with the customers and
understanding the business context,
uniquely in software engineering, it
feels like
the earliest levels are insulated from
all of that. You have your your tech
lead, tech leads handing out tasks, and
then the early level engineers just
given task just convert it into code.
And this sounds like you know, that
part's relatively solved. And if not
now, maybe I I'd be surprised if a year
or two from now wasn't like completely
solved. Um and I I think that could
scare a lot of junior engineers cuz they
they would think you're going to expect
me to graduate from college or start
working as a software engineer, and then
I would have the senior engineer
expectations.
Um what would you say to the the scared
software engineer that's just entering
the industry to all this change?
Yeah, you know, I think um
what I would remind them that, you know,
we as people who hire and build
organizations of software engineers, and
and they as people who have are building
software engineering careers, have have
really
um aligned incentives, right? Like you
know,
it it's not valuable to hire a bunch of
people and set them up to fail. Like
that's
nobody wants that. It's it's it's not an
outcome uh that is good for anybody. And
so, yeah, we're going to need to figure
out how do you support people on on that
path? How do you help people learn those
things? How do you give them the right
guardrails, you know? Hey, that first
time that you go out and talk to a
customer, yeah, it's going to be scary.
My My first time talking to an AWS
customer,
I was you know was
I was was super scary, but you know, I I
I got a bunch of help with that and I
got a bunch of advice and I got a bunch
of mentorship and I got a bunch of
feedback and I got better and better at
that over time and I think that's
exactly what these things look like is,
you know, you start off and you you
start small and and and and you learn,
you know, as you go and and and so that
feedback loop goes faster. And so I
don't expect that people coming in
from college or
you know, will will will come in with
all of this knowledge. I think, you
know, it's never been true that people
coming into technical or engineering
career straight out of college know
everything. Or any career for that
matter, right? Like you talk to to
teachers about, you know, what they've
learned on their job versus what they
learned, you know, studying.
Uh you know, they learn a huge amount in
in in things like internships and and
and so on and and over the course of a
career.
Um or doctors or or anybody in, you
know, in in a field like that. Um
and so yeah, it is going to be about
learning and I think the emphasis on
what people learn is going to be
different.
I think it is going to require,
you know, leaders like me who,
you know, care deeply about, you know,
hiring and and and developing folks
early in their career to be really
thoughtful about what, you know, what
does that new letter look like and
um
and you know, we're we're doing a lot of
that thinking. I think people are doing
that kind of thinking across the
industry.
Uh and uh
yeah, it's changing fast. It's It's
uncertain. It's It's It's an interesting
time to to to be graduating. But again,
like it's a super exciting time. I think
that's just the the the scale of the
opportunity is bigger than it's ever
been.
Sounds like your advice for senior
engineers is different from that of
junior engineers. What What is your
thinking there? Yeah, I mean, I think
you know, I think for for folks there
the challenges is is how do you you
know, how do you retain the value of of
this incredible experience and knowledge
that you've gained over a career
while you know, not falling behind
while learning how to you know, best
best use the tools.
And you know, when I look at
senior folks, this is a is a challenge,
you know, hit of them. I think a lot of
people have found themselves in
influence and and and leadership type
positions where they aren't hands-on
building, you know, every day and I
think it's going to be harder and harder
to be
in that kind of role
and
be able to influence and advise in a
um
in a relevant way in a in a in a
positive way.
Um and so really I think my advice for
folks is is is you kind of got to get
building. Like you got to get back in
get back into it. You need to
deeply understand how the practice of
building software and the practice of
designing software has changed and and
is continuing to change.
And and so the challenge is how do I you
know, really take advantage of all of
this knowledge and expertise that I've
built up in my career
and be super curious and be super
hands-on and really be in the details.
And the good news for that Well, I think
there's two bits of good news. One of
them is because of these new tools, you
know, time spent as a practitioner is is
so much more leveraged than it is today.
You can build
so such cool stuff, you know, in in
during that period of time the the
amount of kind of
wasted time and boilerplate and so on is
is so much smaller and so you really do
have this opportunity.
And the other one is again, like why did
you know,
why did we get into this space? Well,
I didn't get into it so I could go to
meetings and sound smart. I got into it
because I love learning and because I
love building technology and because I
love, you know, solving my customers
problems and because I love, you know,
learning about new, you know, new
technologies and learning new things.
And And there's more opportunity to do
that than ever before. Again, you know,
because of this this new set of tools
and the leverage that comes with them.
And so, really is getting back to,
you know, why are you here? Why did you
get into this career? And I think it
really gets us
as technology-focused people
closer to
the our original answer to that.
It's really obvious to me right now when
I speak to, you know, practitioners,
you know, who and who isn't
using a, you know, modern set of
agentic-powered
developer practices. Right? And the
people who are, um, have these really
interesting things to say about the
strengths and weaknesses of those
approaches and the work that still needs
to be done and the integrations that
still need to be done and the things
that are working and aren't. Uh, and the
people who aren't,
you know, using them hands-on
have such
a poor mental model of how they work,
what they're good at, what they're not
good at, that the things they say about
them tend to vary tend to be essentially
fiction.
Um, and so, you know, I think we are in
this minute that if you aren't doing it
hands-on, your opinion about it is is
very likely to be completely wrong.
And that takes a level of humility to
admit that, you know, is is is tough.
You know, it's it's tough for folks with
fancy titles and it's tough for folks
with with distinguished careers. Uh, but
I I think it's a must.
I I feel like there's a common sentiment
among software engineers when they when
they work with someone who is a you
know, quote unquote tech lead but
they're not really hands-on. So, they've
kind of been in the docks for the last 5
years or or so and there's these minor
things they can tell that this person
doesn't actually understand the
underlying thing and sounds like that
gap will widen with these new tools,
which is if you're you're looking at
things from 1,000 ft up and you're not
actually using the tools, that's just
another thing that separates you from
the people who are actually building
where you'll be very out of touch. And I
I think uh you know, when I look at I
think that's always been true. I think
it is wider than you know, ever before.
Um
and but when I look at the
you know, engineering leaders that I've
really respected and learned a huge
amount from over my career. Uh you know,
for example, some of the folks who who
built S3, you know, 20 years ago,
that was such a successful product
because those folks were so deep in the
details and so grounded on the use cases
and so deep in the economics and and
really just did um
you know, really thought about
uh
both the kind of strategic world of like
how is this cloud thing going to change
the way people want to interact with
storage,
but also the
you know, minute-to-minute details of
what's fast now, what's slow, what's
good, what's bad. And I think you know,
when you think about a extremely
enduring product like S3,
um
at or or EC2, I think it's it's been
that groundedness in the details from
from early on from all levels of
leadership that has made those things
so successful. Um
where you know, other products seemingly
with the same amount of early promise
didn't turn out to be as successful.
I think one of the last topics that I
wanted to ask you about was writing. Um,
you have a ton of awesome posts on your
blog. The style of writing is incredibly
clear.
And I I was curious, why do you write so
much as an engineer?
Writing and and speaking, uh, but
especially writing have this incredible
power.
Um, and
you know, for for technical folks, it's
this incredible multiplier in being able
to take these ideas that's in your head
and share them with the world.
Um,
and you know, you can can take a set of
technical ideas in your head and share
them with the world by building a great
product and that's a fantastic thing to
do.
Uh, you can share them in the world kind
of one-on-one, you know, mentorship,
teach people, learn, small groups, also
a great way to spend time.
But the
multiplication factor of doing a talk or
even more of of writing something is so
much higher, right? Like, there are so
many more people that you can share that
with and it lasts for a much longer
period of time.
Um,
and so just having something written on
my blog even that I wrote like a decade
ago that I can share with someone and
say, you know, here's you know, here's
how to think about this problem, here's
an insight that I I I wanted to share
with you. Or or have people discover
that organically is a super powerful.
And so, writing lets you scale out the
impact of your expertise in in space and
time in a way that's really hard to do
in other media. I think with with video
and with podcasts and so on, you know,
we've seen other ways to do that. But I
think writing remains kind of uniquely
powerful.
And then there's this also this idea,
which is this kind of kind of core
belief culturally at Amazon, and I've
obviously been in
affected by this over the years, that
you know, writing forces a level of
mental clarity that speaking, making
slide decks, etc. doesn't. And you know,
that's something that is also really
been my experience of sitting down
to write something down forces me to
think that through
at a depth that I wouldn't have been
been forced to think it through without
that.
Um and so it's all one of you know, your
early conversations with was with Leslie
Lamport, who kind of takes that a step
further and say, "Hey, you know, it's
formal mathematics that is the next step
there." And I I love that point. Um
but I I I think writing is this really
accessible thing for for people to do
that does force a level of thinking. And
so I do a lot of writing, sometimes just
for myself, right? Like I'll I'll write
not ever intending to share it with
anybody,
but just to sharpen my own thinking on a
on a particular point. And so it's some
of that combination of three things,
right? Like I just I just have something
to say and I want to say it. Um you
know, I have something to say and I want
to scale it out in in time and space.
And I want to sharpen my own thinking on
a on a subject um
or or or the thinking of a small group
on a subject in a way that writing is
just a super powerful tool to to do.
Definitely. Yeah, I remember being
surprised early in my career, I had a
manager tech lead who we would write
these these docs on you know, either the
designs or the strategy, and he said,
"Even if you just wrote it and you threw
it away, it would still be worthwhile
because you'll realize things as you're
writing, and that clarity will save you
a lot of time down the road.
Um and it's interesting to me cuz a lot
of engineers
they complain about writing docs. Docs
and you know, all the stuff around the
code. They kind of they kind of hate
that. They say it's a sign of slow, big
company processes and you know, what
would you say to an engineer like that
who's saying, "I just just let me write
the code." Yeah, and that's a great you
know, it's a great point and I think it
really depends on the level of problem
you're trying to solve. And so, you
know, if I look at
I'm going to pick on UML for a minute
here, right? Like it's a sort of
semi-formal software design process and
not one that I've ever found useful
because I think it just happens at the
wrong semantic level. I think it's
bothered with details at a level that
aren't helpful.
Um
and I think a lot of the let's go off
and document this has has a similar
problem, right? Like does this actually
require that level of reflection and
thinking?
Um
and so I think what, you know, for me
separates a valuable doc writing and and
thinking process from a busy work
process is understanding what you're
getting out of it.
And what you're getting out of it might
be an artifact to share with the future,
which is super valuable.
Um either your future self if you've got
a terrible memory like me or, you know,
new teams, new people, people ex- you
know,
or I want to share something with
customers or I want to share something
with the world. And so that's super
valuable.
Or I want to write down something so I
can think through a really difficult,
often one-way door kind of
un- hard to change technical decision or
API design decision.
And I'm not going to do that every time
I make a technical decision. It's not
worth it because a lot of those
technical decisions are either easy or
or not as critical or can be just be
taken back if we figure out they're
wrong.
But I am going to to spend my time that
way when there are key decisions to
make, when there are key
um
insights to to find.
And
I think, you know, and so
it is that like what is the purpose of
writing?
Uh that
uh is that that separates
well-spent time from
poorly spent time.
Now, there are people who still don't
like writing even when it's well-spent
time, even when it's like
you know, you have to explain this piece
of technology to, you know, to a future
team. Um
I think that's a skill worth developing.
You know, sometimes you you do need to,
you know, uh eat your vegetables, uh you
know, and it's it's it is a skill worth
getting good at.
Um
and you know, especially in
documenting the core kind of technical
decisions behind a design is is so
useful. And that's useful in two ways,
by the way. Like one of them is as we
think about building a big system,
um we make thousands of decisions. And
some of those decisions are very
carefully chosen, very particular, and
very impactful.
And some of those decisions are
the best thing we could guess in the
moment based on having no data to make
that decision.
And it's super useful for people who are
coming in to improve that system down
the line to be able to look at the
design and say which of these things
were very carefully chosen and thought
through, and which of these things were
arbitrary.
And because the arbitrary things like
okay, well, I'm going to change that and
I'm going to just go ahead and change
that cuz I have better data now. I've
watched the system run. I can go and
change those. And these other ones were
like, well, let me really engage with
the reason that we made this decision.
Maybe it was non-obvious. Maybe there
was some some more advanced thinking.
And so, being able to kind of understand
the amount of thought that went into a
decision is almost as important as
understanding what that thought was. You
had a really interesting blog post. This
was um
from a while back. It it's titled the
four hobbies and apparent expertise.
And you introduced this really
interesting idea. It's a 2 by 2 matrix.
And on one side, there's doing versus
discussing. And on the other side,
there's the hobby and the gear. Maybe I
can overlay it for people who want to
see. And then later you you kind of
liken that to your career and how I
guess maybe we can imagine the hobby is
is actually coding. And maybe the gear
is
let's just say it's like your dev setup
or something like that. You talked about
these two aspects of being in in
depending on which quadrant you are,
which is there's this trade-off between
expertise and visibility. Where imagine
you're really into coding and you're
really into doing, you're going to be
phenomenal in terms of expertise, but
maybe not as visible, cuz you're not
talking with everyone about how cool
your setup is and and all of that. And
on the flip side, if you're really into
the gear, or maybe your setup in this
case, and you're really into discussing,
you're you're on all the messaging posts
and that, you might not actually be that
good at at coding, but you're very
visible and you have this apparent
competence.
And I thought that trade-off was really
interesting, because I've seen that so
much in software engineering, too, is
there might be someone who's
really quiet coder. They never write
anything, but they know everything, cuz
they've just been in the weeds all the
time. And then there are people on the
complete opposite end of the spectrum
that writing all the time, speaking all
the time, but maybe not actually
practicing as much. And my question to
you is, how do you strike that balance?
Cuz obviously too far in either
direction is not optimal. So, how do you
strike that balance?
Yeah, that's uh you know, that's that's
something that I reflect on a on a lot.
Uh you know, and I do explicitly think
that sort of being 100% on either of
those ends is a is a is a is a failure
mode. And I think
you know, I I will say that
I have a lot more
personal enjoyment working with the
people that are 100% on the doing side
and and 0% on the talking side. I I I I
appreciate and and deeply you know,
deeply love their expertise. Um
but I I I do think that you know, they
they could have more impact and and and
leverage if if if they you know, swung a
little bit away from that. Um
you know, I I tend to not enjoy as much
interacting with the people who are 100%
on on on on the speaking side. Um
Uh but I I
and I think they would you know, have a
lot more
relevant things to say
you know, if if if they you know, swung
a little bit back towards the center.
The other challenge of being on a 100%
on the doing side is sort of gets back
to that, how do you find the really
important problems? And you know, if
your head's down in your IDE all day
you could very likely be working on the
wrong thing.
Um you know, something that that isn't
as as important, isn't as impactful. Um
you know, doesn't have these properties
that that people want. So, you know, how
how do you find the optimal balance? Uh
I don't have a have a recipe for you
know, what really is is optimal.
I tend to
do about let's say 75/25
kind of practitioner versus you know
teaching and and and and communicating.
Maybe 80/20 at times. I found that's
about what feels right for me. Um
I would say that, you know, the great
people I work with, you know, from sort
of 90/10 on that scale up to about 50/50
on that scale. I think, you know,
outside of those, you know, folks tend
to
um
you know, tend to get into trouble
um as practitioners, right? Like, you
know, there people whose job it is to
be, you know, communicators and and
that's great as long as they have the
curiosity and and are clear about what
they, you know, know and and and don't
know. Um
But you know, I found that sweet spot at
that sort of 75/25 point in in in my
career and and that's what's what's
worked for me. I think
um
And I I I think in this moment where
things are changing so fast, there's so
much to learn,
um you know, swinging a little bit more
towards the practitioner side, I think
generally will help people. But again,
you don't want to go too far that way
because then you lose the
um you know, what's important for you
that comes with interacting with the
outside world. On the doing versus
discussing axis, I I kind of view the
doing one as if you were too far, you
would be underrated. And if you were too
far at the discussing, you would be
overrated. Mhm. And
if for someone who's structuring their
career,
uh would you say it's better to be
overrated or underrated?
I think long-term, you know, if if
you're if you're using that terminology,
it's probably better to be underrated. I
think
you know, being
being overrated can feel great
in the moment, um but is rarely
sustainable.
Uh and and and really sort of gets you
where
to where you you you you need to be. I
really enjoy, you know,
uh,
you know, things like sports and and
and, you know, these sort of creative
hobbies and and, uh, you know, crafts
because it it it does,
you know, turn that, um,
let's say perception and reality
knob to to very much reality, right?
Like as a as a as a sports person, you
can't you can't fool the world for very
long. Uh, it it it very quickly becomes,
uh, you know, very obvious, you know,
who who can and who can't. Uh,
you know, I think as a as a crafts
person, the same, right? It it very
quickly becomes,
um,
obvious [clears throat] who who can and
who can't. And I think it takes a little
bit longer in a field like ours where
there always is so much kind of
qualitative stuff that goes on.
Um, but I think long-term when I look
at, you know, careers that I really
admire and people I really admire, uh,
they tend to be people who are
personally very honest about their level
of of knowledge and understanding and
skill.
So, people who walk the walk, not
necessarily talk the talk. I see. Yeah,
about engineers that you admire, I'd be
curious cuz you have worked at AWS and
for such a long time and you have seen
so many legendary engineers.
Who at AWS do you look up to and and
why?
Yeah, I mean, you know, just fantastic.
One of the blessings of working at a
place like AWS is I get to work with so
many great people. Um,
you know, maybe because he's retired,
I'll I'll I'll talk a little bit about
Al Vermeulen. Uh, was was one of the
sort of early engineers at AWS and,
um,
original,
say, huge contributor to the design of
S3, a really big contributor to the
design of a lot of a lot of our database
services over time.
Um, Al was actually the the CTO of
Amazon for a for a period of time when
he realized, I think,
that wasn't the job he wanted to do. Um,
but I, you know, what I really admired
about uh about Al from early in my
career is,
you know, very clearly he was somebody
who deeply understood the things he was
he was doing. And he could work in these
two modes, right? Like, you know, I I
have a great um memory of a sort of
2010-ish, uh
you know, arguing with Al about some of
the edge cases in in the the Paxos
paper. And, you know, he was super deep
at that level, but could also get up to
the the really kind of executive level
and talk about, you know, cloud strategy
and the way we should be explaining
things to people and some of the, you
know, sort of fundamental things that we
need to be building.
Um,
and I really admired that ability to
work sort of almost at at at every
level. And I was like, "Wow, you know,
this is this is something I aspire to."
Um, and uh you know, want to model my
want to model my own career after.
Um,
and so, you know, that's I I think that
is uh you know, the kind of person I've
really, you know, really enjoyed working
with is is people who do have that, you
know, do have that breadth. Um,
and I think, you know, one of the other
things that is you know, really
admirable about a lot of these folks is,
you know, they
they don't want to be celebrities,
right? They they they want to do cool
work for, you know, have an impact, do
great stuff for customers, you know,
optimize for having impact. You know,
for people who want to continue their
engineering education and really remain
on top of things, deeply understand the
technology, do you have any top
technical book recommendations? You
know, anybody who's building distributed
system things, I I I highly recommend uh
Martin Kleppmann's book.
I think there's a second edition of that
coming out, you know, soon. Um
there's a new edition of quantitative
systems design book, which I also think
is is is great. Sorry, Hennessy and
Patterson's computer architecture book.
This this is a super super useful one
that covers a
ton of ground. I read a ton of you know,
fiction and and non-fiction and and
mostly papers when I'm reading technical
things I find you know, I find engaging
at that level you know, more more useful
for me.
And by the way, that's that's become way
more accessible now. You know, one of
the great ways to dive into a paper is
you know, hey
you know, hey Claude summarize this for
me and then then I can dive into it and
and and read you know, the author's
words and I I find that mode is great
and and this is super accessible for
people who haven't been able to read
papers in in the past. Um
but uh
you know, and then there's also a ton of
insight in in some really old stuff too.
Uh
for example
um
you know, some of the
algorithms that we used in in in Lambda
to to manage traffic and and manage
bursts of traffic come from Erlang's
work like a hundred years ago on on
managing telephone call centers
and and his book about that and um
and so you know, folks also shouldn't
think that oh well, the industry is
changing super fast and so I should only
read recent things like there's still
incredible insights in some of the you
know, older work
and in the foundations of
computing and infrastructure and and and
networking and and computer science that
there is um
you know, more again more maybe more
leverage than ever before you know
deeply understanding those topics.
And then last question for you is if you
could go back to your younger self when
you just joined AWS and give yourself
some advice what would you say?
I think maybe I'd be a little bit
bolder. I really loved the team that I
worked with and and you know
you know especially in EC2 and and in
the early days in EBS and I think I was
a little bit more hesitant than was
optimal about leaving those teams and
and looking for the next thing
um you know as
um
you know my
own learning and impact kind of you know
tapered off a little bit in in in those
those places and so
you know I think I've changed
organizations kind of
in a big way four times in my career and
maybe five or six would have been
optimal not a lot more but but some more
uh and so you know don't don't hesitate
uh to
think about you know what am I learning
and who am I learning from and is there
a better environment to to to do that
you know more quickly and
uh and and to learn more things and you
know I'm highly personally highly
motivated by being able to follow my
curiosity and every time I've done that
in my career I found that a
valuable move
uh and uh and something that I've you
know personally enjoyed. Awesome. Okay,
well thank you so much for your time I I
really appreciate it Mark uh thank you
for sharing with uh the audience. This
has been super fun. Thanks so much.
Thank you for listening to the podcast.
It's a passion project of mine that I've
really enjoyed building. Another passion
project that I've been working on kind
of in secret is building an ergonomic
keyboard that I wish existed and I
finally have a prototype so I'd love to
show you what we've built. It's ultra
low profile and ergonomic and I couldn't
find anything like it on the market, so
that's why we built it. I'll put a link
to the keyboard in the description. You
can take a look and learn more about the
project there. We could definitely use
your support. Also, if you have any
feedback for me about the show, I'd love
to hear it. Comments on YouTube have led
to guests coming on like Ilya Grigoric
and David Fowler. I wasn't aware of them
until someone dropped a comment. Also,
feedback in the comments helped me learn
to reduce the number of cliffhangers in
the intros. So, your comments definitely
make a difference. Please keep letting
me know what you'd like to see more of
in the show, and I'll see you in the
next episode.